and describe that experience. (Laughter) I know it's difficult, eh? But, of course, I don't expect you to do that. You would all be uncomfortable and embarrassed. And so imagine an 11-year-old girl in the Middle East who was not educated about sexuality, who was taken from her comfort zone, her family, who witnessed the execution of her father and brothers, having to describe in detail the rape that she faced in a culture where talking about sexuality is taboo. Her only way of recovering her honor is to hide the crime, believe she was married against her will, or deny the events out of shame and fear of being rejected. I interviewed a girl who I will call "Ayda." She was purchased by an ISIS leader, or emir, together with 13 other girls aged between 11 and 18 years old. Amongst the group were her three nieces and two cousins. The 14 girls were taken to a house full of ISIS fighters. An imam was present who made it clear that their religion was wrong, and the only good path was to accept Islam and marry a Muslim man. The emir wrote the names of the girls on 14 small pieces of paper. Two ISIS fighters would pick a piece of paper each. They would call out the name written on the paper, and those girls were forcibly taken into another room. While the emir and the imam heard the two girls screaming as they were being raped, they began laughing. Both were telling the other girls that the two girls should enjoy the experience instead of screaming. After a while, the girls were brought back into the room. They were in shock and were bleeding. They confirmed that they had been married and suffered a lot of pain. It is important to consider the fact that they had been raised to believe in sexual intercourse with one man in their lifetime: their husband. The only connection that they could make in their shocked state is to define their rape as marriage. Before the next two girls were taken to be raped, Ayda made a terrifying decision. As the oldest of the group, she convinced the emir to let them use the bathroom in order to wash themselves before marriage. Ayda had been told by one of the girls that she noticed rat poison in the bathroom. The 14 girls decided to end their suffering by drinking the poison. Before the poison took full effect, they were discovered by ISIS and taken to the hospital, where they survived. ISIS decided to separate the girls and sell them individually. Ayda was taken to another house and brutally raped after she attempted again to kill herself with her headscarf. She was beaten and raped every two days. After four months in captivity, Ayda found the courage to escape. She never saw the other 13 girls again. I interviewed Ayda multiple times. She was willing to speak to me because she had heard from other victims that there was a woman from the UN who understood her complicated culture. I looked into her eyes and listened deeply to the stories of her darkest hours. We established a personal connection that continues to this day. My upbringing made it easy for me to understand her extreme sense of shame and her fear of being rejected. These types of investigations are not only about gathering information and evidence, but they're also about victim support. The bonds I established with the victims strengthens their confidence and willingness to seek justice. As she considered her escape, Ayda, like all Yazidi survivors, faced a dilemma: Should she continue to suffer the abuse of her captors, or would it be better to return home, where she would face shame, rejection and possibly honor killing? I know all too well the pain of being rejected by my Moroccan community in Belgium, and I did not want this to happen to the Yazidi community. So a group of concerned entities, including the UN, NGOs, politicians and members of the Yazidi community approached a religious leader, Baba Sheikh. After many meetings, he realized that these girls had not disrespected their religion by being forcibly converted to Islam and married to ISIS fighters. Instead, they have been abducted, raped and sexually enslaved. I am happy to report that, after our meetings, Baba Sheikh announced publicly that the survivors should be treated as victims and embraced by the community. This message was heard throughout the community and eventually reached the survivors being held captive by ISIS. After his declaration of support, the survivors were motivated to escape from ISIS as Ayda has done, and many young Yazidi women took the bold step and returned home to their communities. Baba Sheikh's public pronouncement saved the lives of many young Yazidi women, both in captivity and after their escape. Sadly, not all religious leaders agreed to talk with us. Some victims had far worse outcomes than the Yazidis. For example, only 43 of the 500-600 victims from the Shia Turkmen community were able to return home after escaping ISIS. Some of them were advised by their family to stay with ISIS or commit suicide in order to save the honor of the family. Germany established a project to support survivors of ISIS by providing psychosocial support and housing for 1,100 women and children, including Ayda. I visited Ayda several times during my work. I am so proud of her and the other victims. The progress they have made is remarkable. It is really moving to see how many of them, despite their struggles, have benefited from this program. The program includes individual and group counseling, art therapy, music therapy, sport activities, language courses, school and other integration efforts. What I observed was that removing the victims from an area of conflict to a country at peace had a positive impact on all of them. This project caught the attention of other countries, and they were interested to help more Yazidis. The Yazidi women and girls still call and text me to tell me about their grades at school, fun trips they've taken, or to inform me about their future dreams, like writing a book about what they have faced with ISIS. Sometimes they are sad and feel the need to talk again about the events. I'm not a psychologist, and I have faced secondary PTSD from their horrific stories. But I keep encouraging them to talk, and I keep listening, because I do not want them to feel alone in their suffering. Through these anecdotes, I see a bigger picture emerging. These women and girls are healing. They are no longer afraid to seek justice. Without hope there can be no justice, and without justice there can be no hope. Every 3rd and 15th of August, it's my remembrance day, and I reach out to the Yazidis to let them know that I'm thinking about them. They're always happy when I do that. It's an emotional day for them. This past August, I spoke with Ayda. She was so happy to announce that one of her nieces who was abducted with her was finally released out of ISIS hands in Syria and returned to Iraq. Can you believe that? After four years? Today, her biggest wish is for her whole family, now located across three continents, to be reunited. And I hope they will. When I think about the survivors I work with, I remember the words of an Egyptian doctor, writer and human rights activist, Nawal El Saadawi. In her book, "Woman at Point Zero," she wrote, "Life is very hard, and the only people who really live are those who are harder than life itself." These victims have been through unimaginable pain. But with a little help, they show how resilient they are. Each has their own perspective on what kind of justice she seeks, and I believe deeply that a credible justice process is key to how she reclaims her dignity and finds closure with her trauma. Justice is not only about punishing the perpetrator. It's about victims feeling that crimes committed against them have been recorded and recognized by the rule of law. For me, it has been the experience of a lifetime to work with these survivors. Because I share their sorrow, their language and their culture, we connect on the deepest human level. This itself is an act of healing: to be heard, to be seen, to be given compassion instead of condemnation. When we get so close to people in pain, it creates pain for the investigators, too. My work is challenging, heartbreaking and trauma-inducing. But let me tell you why I do it. When I meet the survivors of these mass atrocities, when I hold their hands and look in their eyes, it does not erase my own pain, but it does make it almost worthwhile. And there's nothing I would rather be doing. When I see these brave survivors struggling to connect again to their own self-worth, to their families, to their place in a society that values them, it is an honor to bear witness; it is a privilege to seek justice. And that is healing, too -- for all of us. Thank you. (Applause)
y describan esa experiencia. (Risas) Sé que es difícil, ¿no? Pero, por supuesto, no espero que hagan eso. Todos se sentirían incómodos y avergonzados Y entonces imaginen a una chica de 11 años en Oriente Medio que no fue educada sobre la sexualidad, que fue sacada de su zona de confort, su familia, que fue testigo de la ejecución de su padre y hermanos, teniendo que describir en detalle la violación a la que se enfrentó en una cultura donde lo sexual es tabú. Su única manera de recuperar su honor es esconder el crimen, creer que fue casada contra su voluntad, o negar los acontecimientos por vergüenza o miedo a ser rechazada. Entrevisté a una chica a la que voy a llamar "Ayda". Fue comprada por un líder de ISIS, o emir, junto con otras 13 chicas de edades comprendidas entre los 11 y 18 años. En el grupo estaban sus tres sobrinas y dos primas. Las 14 chicas fueron llevadas a una casa llena de combatientes del ISIS. Un imam estuvo presente, que dejó claro que su religión era errónea, y el único camino bueno era aceptar el islam y casarse con un hombre musulmán. El emir escribió los nombres de las chicas en 14 pedacitos de papel. Dos combatientes del ISIS elegirían un pedazo de papel cada uno. Gritarían el nombre escrito en el papel, y esas chicas serían llevadas a la fuerza a otra habitación. Mientras el emir y el imam escuchaban a las dos chicas gritar, mientras eran violadas, empezaron a reírse. Ambos les decían a las otras chicas que las dos chicas deberían disfrutar la experiencia en lugar de gritar. Después de un rato, las chicas fueron llevadas de vuelta. Estaban en shock y sangrando. Confirmaron que habían sido casadas y sufrido mucho dolor. Es importante considerar el hecho de que habían sido criadas para creer en las relaciones sexuales con un hombre en sus vidas: su marido. La única conexión que pudieron hacer en su estado de choque fue definir sus violaciones como matrimonio. Antes de que las siguientes dos chicas fueran llevadas para ser violadas, Ayda tomó una terrible decisión. Como la mayor del grupo, convenció al emir de dejarlas usar el baño para lavarse antes del matrimonio. Una de las chicas dijo a Ayda que notó veneno matarratas en el baño. Las 14 chicas decidieron terminar con su sufrimiento bebiendo el veneno. Antes de que el veneno tuviera pleno efecto, fueron descubiertas por el ISIS y llevadas al hospital, donde sobrevivieron. El ISIS decidió separar a las chicas y venderlas individualmente. Ayda fue llevada a otra casa y brutalmente violada después de que intentara de nuevo suicidarse con su velo. Fue golpeada y violada cada dos días. Tras cuatro meses de cautividad, Ayda encontró el valor para escapar. Nunca volvio a ver a las otras 13 chicas. Entrevisté a Ayda varias veces. Estaba dispuesta a hablar conmigo porque escuchó de otras víctimas que allí había una mujer de ONU que comprendía su complicada cultura. La miré a los ojos y escuché atentamente las historias de su hora más oscura. Establecimos una conexión personal que continúa el día de hoy. Mi educación me facilitó la comprensión de su extremo sentido de la vergüenza y miedo a ser rechazada. Este tipo de investigación no consiste solo en recopilar información y evidencias, sino también en apoyar a las víctimas. Los lazos que establezco con las víctimas fortalecen su confianza y su deseo de buscar justicia. Mientras consideraba su escape, Ayda, como todos los supervivientes yazidíes, se enfrentó a un dilema: ¿debería continuar sufriendo el abuso de sus captores, o sería mejor volver a casa, donde se enfrentaría la vergüenza, el rechazo y posible muerte por honor? Conozco demasiado bien el dolor de ser rechazada por mi comunidad marroquí en Bélgica, y no quería que esto le ocurriera a la comunidad yazidí. Un grupo de entidades interesadas, incluyendo la ONU, varias ONG, políticos y miembros de la comunidad yazidí, nos acercamos al líder religioso, Baba Sheik. Tras muchos encuentros, se dio cuenta de que estas chicas no habían faltado al respeto a la religión al ser forzadas a convertirse al islam y casarse con combatientes del ISIS. Que, en cambio, fueron secuestradas, violadas y esclavizadas sexualmente. Me complace informar que, tras nuestras reuniones, Baba Sheik anunció públicamente que las supervivientes deberían ser tratadas como víctimas y aceptadas por la comunidad. Este mensaje se escuchó en toda la comunidad y finalmente llegó hasta las supervivientes cautivas por ISIS. Tras esa declaración de apoyo, las supervivientes estuvieron motivadas de escapar del ISIS como hizo Ayda, y muchas jóvenes yazidíes dieron el valiente paso y volvieron a casa a sus comunidades. El pronunciamiento público de Baba Sheik salvó las vidas de muchas jóvenes yazidíes tanto en cautiverio como después de su escape. No todos los líderes religiosos aceptaron hablar con nosotros. Algunas víctimas tuvieron peores desenlaces que las yazidíes. Por ejemplo, solo 43 de las 500 a 600 víctimas de la comunidad chiita turcomana fueron capaces de regresar a casa tras escapar del ISIS. Algunas fueron aconsejadas por sus familias para permanecer en ISIS o cometer suicidio para salvar el honor de la familia. Alemania estableció un proyecto para apoyar a las supervivientes del ISIS proporcionando apoyo psicosocial y vivienda a 1100 mujeres y niños, incluyendo a Ayda. Visité a Ayda varias veces durante mi trabajo. Estoy muy orgullosa de ella y de las otras víctimas. El progreso que han hecho es sorprendente. Es realmente conmovedor ver cuántas de ellas, a pesar de sus dificultades, se han beneficiado de este programa. Este programa incluye asesoramiento individual y colectivo, terapia artística, terapia musical, actividades deportivas, cursos de idiomas, colegio y otros esfuerzos de integración. Lo que observé es que alejar a las víctimas de un área en conflicto a un país en paz tenía un impacto positivo en todas ellas. Este proyecto llamó la atención de otros países, y estaban interesados en ayudar a más yazidíes. Las mujeres y niñas yazidíes aún me llaman y escriben para contarme sobre sus notas en el colegio, viajes divertidos que han hecho o para informarme sobre sus sueños futuros, como escribir un libro sobre lo que han enfrentado con el ISIS. A veces están tristes y sienten la necesidad de volver a hablar sobre los eventos. No soy psicóloga y me he enfrentado a un TEPT secundario por sus terribles historias. pero las sigo alentando a hablar, y sigo escuchando, porque no quiero que se sientan solas en su sufrimiento. A través de estas anécdotas, veo emerger una imagen más grande. Estas mujeres y niñas están sanando. Ya no tienen miedo de buscar justicia. Sin esperanza no puede haber justicia, y sin justicia no puede haber esperanza. Todos los 3 y 15 de agosto, son mi día del recuerdo, y me acerco a los yazidíes para dejarles saber que pienso en ellos. Siempre están felices cuando hago eso. Es un día emotivo para ellos. El agosto pasado, hablé con Ayda. Estaba muy feliz de anunciar que una de sus sobrinas, que fue secuestrada con ella había sido finalmente liberada de las manos del ISIS en Siria y regresó a Irak. ¿Pueden creer eso? ¿Después de cuatro años? Hoy, su mayor deseo para toda su familia, ahora ubicada en tres continentes, es reunirse. Y espero que lo hagan. Cuando pienso en las supervivientes con que trabajo, recuerdo las palabras de una médica egipcia, escritora, y activista de derechos humanos, Nawal El Saadawi. En su libro "Mujer en punto cero", escribió: "La vida es muy dura y las únicas personas que viven realmente son aquellas más duras que la vida misma". Estas víctimas han pasado por un dolor inimaginable. Pero con un poco de ayuda, muestran cuán resilientes son. Cada una tiene su propia perspectiva del tipo de justicia que busca, y creo firmemente que un proceso de justicia creíble es clave para cómo ella reclama su dignidad y pone fin a su trauma. La justicia no es solo sobre castigar al perpetrador. Se trata de que las víctimas sientan que los crímenes cometidos han sido registrados y reconocidos por el imperio de la ley. Para mí, ha sido la experiencia de toda una vida trabajar con estas supervivientes. Porque comparto su pena, su idioma y su cultura, nos conectamos en el nivel humano más profundo. Esto en sí mismo es un acto de curación: ser escuchada, ser vista, o tener compasión en lugar de condena. Cuando nos acercamos tanto a personas con dolor esto también crea dolor a los investigadores. Mi trabajo es exigente, descorazonador e inductor de trauma. Pero déjenme decirles por qué lo hago. Cuando me encuentro con las supervivientes de estas atrocidades masivas, cuando tomo sus manos y miro en sus ojos, no borra mi propio dolor, pero hace que casi merezca la pena. Y no hay nada distinto que preferiría estar haciendo. Cuando veo a estas valientes supervivientes luchando para conectarse de nuevo con su propia valía, con sus familias, con su lugar en una sociedad que las valora, es un honor dar testimonio; es un privilegio buscar justicia. Y eso también es curativo para todos nosotros. Gracias (Aplausos)